International Typographical Union; Collection apap142
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
International Typographical Union Collection
1870-1936
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
apap142
0.4 cubic ft.
The International Typographical Union was a trade union for the printing trade for newspapers and other media. This collection contains proceedings, programs and photographs of the annual meetings and conventions.
Biographical / Historical
The International Typographical Union (ITU) was founded on May 3, 1852 in New York City. The ITU was a U.S. trade union for the printing trade for newspapers and other media. The original group had 14 cities that were split up into local unions. The first union was in Indianapolis. The ITU also had chapters in Canada. To be a member of the union, a person had to be a mailer or a newspaper writer. The ITU supported a variety of strikes including boycotting the Lost Angeles Times. However, some riots turned violent. On October 1, 1910, James B. Mc Namara, a member of the ITU and his brother placed a bomb in the Lost Angeles Times building. While the brothers were convicted, the Lost Angeles Times remained a non-union shop and continued to not support the ITU.
Members of the ITU supported an eight-hour work day, and joined other AFL unions during the Great Depression to support organizing. Eventually, due to advancement in technologies, the ITU was not financially stable enough to stand on its own, so members began to try and merge with unions like the Newspaper Guild and the International Brotherhood of Teamsters. These mergers however, failed and on December 31, 1986 the ITU dissolved. Members joined the Communication Workers of America.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains proceedings, souvenirs/programs and photographs of the annual meetings and conventions.
Arrangement
The collection is uarranged chronologically. There are no series.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The records of the International Typographical Union were donated to the M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives in two accessions. The provenance of the earlier accession is unknown. Mary Ann Darnaby donated all the convention souvenirs/programs in 2025. They belonged to her husband's great-grandfather who was a member of ITU #1 in Indianapolis, working at Hollenbeck Press.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted.
International Typographical Union., 1852-1986; Labor unions--History--19th century; Labor unions--History--20th century; Printing--United States--History; Labor
- ITU Proceedings, 1870-1872 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- ITU Proceedings, 1873-1876 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- ITU Proceedings, 1878-1880 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- ITU Proceedings, 1881-1882 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- ITU Proceedings, 1884-1885 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- ITU Proceedings, 1886-1887 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- ITU Proceedings, 1902 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Convention Souvenir (Program), 1903 (Oversize 1)
- Convention Souvenir (Program), 1906-1910 (Oversize 1)
- Convention Souvenir (Program), 1911-1912 (Oversize 2)
- Convention Souvenir (Program), 1915-1918 (Oversize 2)
- Convention Souvenir (Program), 1920 (Oversize 2)
- Panoramic Delegate Group Photograph at Convention, 1927; 1936 (Flat-file 1)